Hello guys, welcome. Good morning, good
evening. Welcome to another episode of S
talk show. So we going to code uh
mathematics. So I'm this is my work
session. So I'm just going to work
coding my stuff.info
that's my website of 13,000 files
written in the past 30 years. my
keyboard. This is ultimate hacking
keyboard too. I have reviews on YouTube.
Okay. And let's show you my screen.
Okay. So screen
and uh let's show today's talk show. So
we going to do several things. Okay. So
just my walking session. If you are
here, say hi. Love to see your comments
pop out chat in real time.
You comment, I answer. So if you have
questions for me, you can comment. Okay.
So let me check. Video check. Good.
Audio check. Good.
Okay. We're going to do Okay. Uh we're
going to do uh mathematics like quite a
few uh mathematics like special plane
curves. So these are fantastic. So if
you are a student, if you are young
learning calculus, mathematics,
sciences, engineering, you'll usually
enjoy my talk show. But my talk show is
not professional. So I may rant, I may
swear, but
but it's truthful. It's genuine. Okay?
So you're going to I'm us so I'm a nerd.
I usually talk about mathematics,
programming, lots of that. So today I'm
we are going to do a lot of exponential
curve logarithms in in wam language and
javascript. Okay. Okay. So for example
this is wam language beautiful. Uh so
you are seeing that there it's a
beautiful um Taurus. Okay.
Wuam language the best pro uh the most
uh advanced programming language by far.
Okay. So, so anyway, so let's do what I
need to do. Okay, this might be boring.
So, if you are watching offline, play at
1.7 speed usually or 1.5 minimum.
So, anyway, I'm just go slow. So,
today's drink is power juice.
Uh, juice plus energy drink.
[snorts]
So in JavaScript I have
JavaScript object reference. Go to the
top. You have JavaScript in depth. Okay.
So that's my project. That's the one of
the best let's say top three best
JavaScript tutorial in depth.
uh anxi.info. Okay. So, if you search my
name, you'll find it. So, I recommend
you watch, you know, you you go check it
out.
Uh uh but now they have like a new book
there. There's this guy who also used
the the name JavaScript in depth. Of
course, that's available for everyone to
use. But he he there's this guy. He
created the book JavaScript in depth. So
now it overtakes my website and he's uh
so I you know I believe he's also you
know he's expert so by this guy. So who
is this written by James M. Snail? Okay.
So what is he uh I'm not sure but I
believe he is part of the JavaScript
ECMAS script you know the like the
committee you know like u member. So I
believe he this this one is probably a
good book. Okay. So let let me let me
run uh let me uh go uh
Rambo. Okay. So let's ask um
so I wanted to do blur my background in
OBS. So that was my question to AI. So
let's ask AI. Uh who is
uh James M. snail who wrote JS in depth.
Okay, so let's see who he is. But
anyway, I wanted to tell you my
JavaScript in-depth project. You know,
it's on my website. Search for it. Oh,
so you if you search for it and let's
see, you'll find it uh now on the on
[snorts] the on the third link,
JavaScript in depth. Okay, exc.info.
info.
Okay. So, but okay. So, let's go back to
this guy and see JavaScript in-depth
book. So, on my website, you can also
find uh
actually I talked a lot of my uh my
review of JavaScript book books
like just go to sudi.info search for
JavaScript you will find tens of uh
essays. So who is James M snail who
wrote JavaScript in depth? So online
he's known as Jazz Snail is a highly
respected software engineer, opensource
contributor and expert in JavaScript run
times. Okay.
Uh okay. That's part of the author
official introduction. That's not so
good because we want to know the real um
like the actual person not the public.
you know public relations whatever the
book
snippet says about who is the author.
Okay. So anyway so current position
senior principal engineer on the cloud
flare workers runtime team [snorts]
cloudflare. Okay you know uh that's a
big corporation I believe NJS longtime
core contributor.
Oh NJS technical steering committee okay
extensively on NJS internals. Okay. TC39
that's you know that's a member of the
JavaScript design committee. Okay.
Author he wrote a book JavaScript in
depth. Okay. So long history on open
source and open standards
including earlier work at IBM on things
like JSON activity streams. He's known
for contributions to web standards,
okay, stream API and he frequently
speaks at conferences about JavaScript
run times. Okay,
so I tr I you know I trust this guy uh
his book is probably good. Okay. Well,
it could be I mean there there you also
need to take into account on the writing
style because for example some of the
greatest mathematicians
they don't write well okay they don't
they can teach well they can do math you
know they are the greatest
mathematicians but they are writings
like
it's not like like you know it's not
very good they are not gifted in like
telling you like teaching you know so so
It depends also depends on the writing.
Okay. So, let's go to today's talk show
and let's just start to uh write down
what we talked about because as my talk
show I usually document what we talked
about. So, press press my Emac system.
So, you can see a screenshot of that has
been moved here. And let's let me
magnify my Emacs font so you can see.
Say hi here. Okay. Good evening here in
Italy. Fantastic. Neoli Italy.
Magnify.
Do it. Do it. Do it.
Okay. Fantastic. Emacs.
My dear life. My life that my life's
work is Emacs.
Okay. So, the pink window shows all my
command course. Okay. So let's move that
here. Okay. Now I have my workstation
set up so you can see everything.
Right. Right. Right. Right. Right.
Recursion by the way. So you are seeing
infinite recursion in real world.
[laughter] Infinite recursion.
[snorts] Okay. So uh Okay. So we grabbed
that screenshot of the guy like who is
this guy? And we need to grab uh kind of
okay. So
uh you know this this big thing you know
like since about 15 years ago they
started to have this very [ __ ]
annoying design. [ __ ] it. Gray on white.
You see
you you know guys listen. Okay, watch
this gray text unreadable
but they became a fashion like like by
by this Google uh design. Oh, we are the
designer the lead the so-called thought
leaders in the industry in JavaScript in
web web devs.
Okay. See gray on white in impossible to
read.
And here too, you know, this is here.
This is worse. Like, can you guys
actually see? Let me magnify. Okay.
Magnify. Magnify. You can Can you see
the gray on white? [ __ ]
Incredible. Insulting. Okay. Because you
these these things are led by this you
know usually they work at Google work at
Firefox Mozilla like they are big shots
know like the GO van the Python [snorts]
[ __ ] it well not [ __ ] it but stupid okay
like they are big shot they tell you
what to do on hacker news you see you
see their articles on blogs on hacker
news million views you know very popular
because we want you know people follow
the uh celebrities
So the these people the web design the
the this the cascading stylesheet
designer they tell you you know we oh we
should have gray on white
[ __ ] idiot okay which began about 15
years ago I have an article on that okay
but first of all let me do a screenshot
of this
okay so uh let's
so so we have a record of this gray on
white insult,
you know, these are supposed to be
leaders of the JavaScript or webdev or
whatever, but but
gray on white [laughter]
[gasps]
[sighs]
and they supposedly like like every time
you read their stuff including Google's
tutorial on webdev, you know, they'll
tell you, oh, by the way, you should
follow area like accessibility like
that's a very important thing for them.
They talk about accessibility for the
blind, for the deaf. Although they they
don't use those word, they they use like
[snorts] for for the differently
enabled, you know, people with with
different vision than you. This these
people this they became
what you know what? So what actually
happened? So what how is it possible?
These people seems to be you know they
want to do good. They want for, you
know, support the disabled or
differently enabled, right? They they
want to do good. But they came out with
this hugely damaging [ __ ]
Why are they they they promote it like
they tell people so they spread idea
like but nobody see like nobody like
it's like the story of the king is naked
you know until a child says the king is
just naked
but that's what they tell you okay so
you got this issue this is this is kind
of the deep state issue okay in USA
of the
Okay. Anyway, so that so let's complete
the screenshot. So we we've done two
screenshots there. Can you see actually?
Okay. So you kind of see that. So press
press and do it again. So they moved
into this directory, my blog. Okay. So
you can you you you have a record now
after you when you watch this video you
know search for my M myar talk show
episode 804 you you'll have a record of
this
okay after 10 years after 20 years you
will see a history okay but now let me
show you the gray on white gray
text on white background
color disease ease. Okay. By the way,
there are two different alternative
spelling for gray. The American way is G
R A Y. The Brit way, they they usually
go with E. E is better because E is more
logical. Great. E, you know, E is
usually pronounced E. So, great. E.
[snorts] If you say G R A Y,
A is usually pronounced a. So, so
normally it would be would become guay
guay text on white background guay text
on background
you see and and we also have the uh the
brand name greyhound bus in USA. So
anyway, so the gray spellings
orthography okay issue. So let me talk
about that. Okay, so let me just write
down gray. The word gray has two
different
athography.
That's a halty way of selling spelling.
Okay. [laughter]
I gota spelling. The American way is
gray with ah.
Okay.
But the bread way is
gray. grape bong with e with uh e. Okay,
so that makes clear a with the versus e
and then you can see which one is
logically more sound. Okay. Now, um, now
capitalize the
beginning of the sentence and make it a
sentence and press a key to make it one
sentence per line formatting style.
Fantastic and beautiful. This is best
showing browser. So now we can see we
digressed so far. We haven't start to do
what we wanted to do. But but so we are
we are talking about the orthography of
the word gray. Where is it? Uh here.
Okay.
So anyway, gray on white. So Oh yeah. So
So let me show you. So the gray on white
began about 2010.
So So I have a collection of the
historic proof. Okay. Collection of the
record. these idiots,
you know, they pretend they are like
they are your boss, you know, they are
the, you know, the leaders in the
programming industry in the design, but
they create, you know, they created this
huge damaging [ __ ]
and this this relates to all the
frameworks, JavaScript frameworks and
mpm like all the whole kind of the the
way they do things, the practice, the
kind of like corruption Okay.
MPM and CSS tailwind wind. [laughter]
Okay. Gray on white. Okay. So, have a
look at this page. Where where does it
begin? You know this gray on white.
Well,
partly it began with a Solaris idiot.
Okay. Like 15 years ago or more, there
began this Solaris. You know one guy say
who who who who started to say oh by the
science of the colors we should have you
know this scientific formula for
balancing the the contrast of colors
therefore this is the best way it's
called solar solarize okay [ __ ] it
begin you know so it began about um
anyway we digress long okay we started I
started to friend.
But anyway, copy that back here and
paste link linkify make it a list show
in browser.
So we started to digress for like almost
20 minutes already.
Okay. on the gray and white design.
Okay.
Now I want so so we were talking about
this book. So you know so we happen to
talk about book the book JavaScript in
depth. Okay. And now don't forget my
JavaScript in depth by Exxari. Okay. So
let's paste that there.
Okay. So you go to JavaScript in depth
then then let's move on to today's
topic. So you go to Oh, okay. So there's
actually the thing I want to fix. So
yeah, so this page should never mind. So
JavaScript. So there's a JavaScript
reference object reference section. So
among the object, you got a math name
space. Okay. So then go down special
object, global object, special object,
object object, array object, function
object, regular expression object, date,
set, map, symbol, int. Int int is a new
one. Okay, int is like two or three
years old, very new. Okay, int uh proxy
promise which uh an iterator and then
and among them you got a static objects
math. Okay, so then in the math object
you have
exponential and logarithm functions.
Okay. And what I want to do is add
graph. Uh add graph so you can see.
Fantastic and beautiful.
So people can see it. Okay, that's what
I'm going to do. So let me read the
comments first.
Are you guys enjoying the show? So let's
see. Hello. So, I'm working on a um
So, let's magnify the font.
Hello. I'm working on a hard fork of
Emacs and building with clawed code I
plan to release later this year and
we'll call it ZMAX.
That would be interesting. Okay. So my
comment would be a lot of people have
tried to do that and ultimately they
failed. Uh a lot of people have tried to
for example uh write a scheme based
Emacs
and a lot of people some some some have
tried to write a commonly based Emacs
but none become really as powerful or
robust and they just fail by the wayside
okay in the past 30 years. So there
exist a scheme based Emacs. There also
exist common uh common list based Emacs.
Okay. So I can show
>> [snorts]
>> uh I can show um okay we digressing. Uh
okay so let's not digress. Okay let's
just I was going to show you articles.
Okay. So, so for example, if you search
for common list
uh
thoughts on common lists and scheme
based Emacs okay so there's article
click copy the link go back here and
paste it so do we want to talk about
that yeah why not let's just digress all
the way
uh uh
paste linkify. Okay. So this article is
written in 2008. So and here you can see
there are uh I show link to there's
hemlock which is a common listbased
emacs. Okay a free emac text editor
passics compliant unix systems. Okay so
that's one of them. Then there is also
uh comedy uh climax. Okay. Don't know if
they're still alive or not. So, okay.
The the URL is gone, but uh Oh, it's
okay. So, this is still fresh. They just
redirected climax still there. Looks
like pretty up to date. I mean, well, at
least Okay, the last update is like
2018,
[laughter]
20 years ago. But at least they updated
the looks, you know, the looks looks
like today's, you know, CSS modern, you
know,
climax. Okay. You know, it's it's fun
when you get old and you have written
blogs for 30 for 20 20 25 years. Me
actually 30 years by now. Oh, Jesus
[ __ ] So I've written blogs since 1996.
So then then you look back look back you
can have a like a glance of history.
Okay. Uh so you can see I mean and and
also then you can revisit and you can
see what's going on you know like what
what happened to them you know. So
anyway, so this climax
the project is like
seems not you know not have have not
been refreshed but they refresh the
website that's very interesting you know
with also with HTTPS
you see so so they actually update the
web page and with CSS but [laughter]
interesting okay so then you go back
then there is Edwin
it which is a scheme based lisp. There's
I believe there's a Wikipedia article
the okay the URL is dead but it's around
okay that that is around I know for sure
and there's lies it's you know so uh
let's see lies
okay so they move to what is this
website
lisp computing interface oh fancy name
this last last change URL 2007. Okay,
dead.
Okay, so you see and and there's there
is e editor. Okay, the Wikipedia page
got killed dead but eed editor when was
when Haskell was you know in the
mainstream Haskell um so that's around
2012 Hascal so people you know people
wanted to oh let's create a editor based
on Hascal
just like Emacs but Haskell
okay so So my comment is that you you
know you you you might try but uh but I
would say it's not easy to be
successful. Okay but anyway but it's a
passage of right you might say so you
know you do it if you are successful
that's great otherwise you know it
became part [snorts] of your experience.
So anyway, it will have support for
Google Chrome browser rendering markdown
and wy week and a a genic integration.
Okay. Anyway, it's a new era. So you are
saying AI based that's okay. So AI based
you know who knows what's going to
happen
and uh actually a lot you know since the
AI today people stopped using editors
like I'm I think I think it's like you
know like people you know doesn't matter
anymore people don't I mean the editor
become less important because humans
stopped actually manually editing
editing the source mode.
Okay. Um,
color blind mode. Okay. You able to use
Emacs push your PL directly from from
Emacs itself. I'm a long-term Vim user.
Came across you from some older keyboard
videos. Yes.
And time capsule. Okay. Uh,
yeah. Sure. In Emacs you can well the
way I upload to my website is I use
rync. Okay. So so so but I usually run
that command in powershell but you can
run it in uh here for example.
Uh you can run all Unix command in eh
shell. In fact there are several shells.
So you can run in eh shell or you can
run in bash you can run in powershell in
within emacs you know. So eh shell is a
shell written in emac lisp itself. So
you can see uh welcome to emac shell and
you can see the source code by describe
function e shell. Okay.
Okay. Then you jump to the source code
there. Here is a source code you know
eacisp. So jump to the directory. So you
can see each is
go to the bottom 4 390 lines of code. Uh
okay. So but John John Wley. So anyway
you know if you don't know about Emacs
you are new. This is fresh to you but to
Emac users this is like old not news.
Okay.
John Waggley is the current um so-called
maintainer of Kuno Emacs, basically the
leader. Okay. [snorts] Um but I haven't
really followed you know the details the
of the KNU Emacs group. So I believe she
is still like the leader right now.
John Wley, he's also a Haskell coder and
uh anyway [snorts] anyway so if you are
new to Emacs then you know this is news
to you okay
uh but to us or people like some of the
people who watch my video these are like
old news because I've been blogging
about the Emacs thing for 30 years. Okay
so so what are we going what are we
doing? So talk show. Yeah. So let's
start to do what I wanted to do today
which is so first job add plot. Okay.
Let's just do them one by one. So so in
in JavaScript you got this function.
Okay. Let's do what I want to do. Okay.
So JavaScript. So in JavaScript this
page you got the function. So I can show
you. So you can see for example that
code. Let's run it exponential. So that
runs the exponential function. This is a
value. Okay. So
put it back syntax collect show in
browser. Okay. Now we just want to plot.
Okay. So how do you plot this? Um
well so hold on a second. So okay. So go
back to uh shell. Close it. Go back to
um [snorts]
yeah. So let's start wam language. Uh
I'm running wam language saw wra mode
plot. So the exponential function is e
ra to um x. Okay. So that's a woofam
language syntax. Let's say -1 to uh
three. Okay. So now go to the woofam
language. Paste it there.
magnify the it
shift enter to run it. Okay, so that's
what it looks like. And um
and if you want the correct aspect
ratio, I mean if you want the uh x-axis
and the yaxis to be
to be in scale, then you say that. So
then it becomes that and then it's hard
to see because this exponential function
grows very fast. Okay. So you don't want
it to be three and then in that case
reduce the to two.
So yeah. So it's still huge. Okay. So
let's see
uh
Yeah. So, uh, okay. So, let's increase
the negative part -2. And this looks
better. Okay. So, that is the
exponential function.
We want to uh we want to uh what we want
to do, we want to make a plot of it.
Yes, of course. Then add it.
Let's do a screenshot.
Okay.
Put it back. The syntax color.
Go to the JavaScript page.
Move uh move the image here.
Showing browser. So there as a
documentation that's great. Okay. So,
okay, that's kind of let's just leave
it. Okay. Uh
uh let's uh exponential. So,
let's rename it. Okay. Exponential.
Uh we don't want the date in the image
file. So let's rename it. Okay.
Something like that. Okay. Let's just
then then Okay. So let's do the next
one.
Hello ACP.
So next one exponential. Okay. Uh this
you know this is interesting because in
JavaScript so we already have a
exponential function. And what does this
do? expM1
it does exponential function but minus
one. Okay. Why? Because
because um some kind of funny business
like when you are doing exponential um
function
when the value is let's see minus one.
So
uh I don't know. So why do they have
this function? I actually I don't know.
So this function in JavaScript. Now
remember this is JavaScript. JavaScript
has this fun function exp1
which computes the same as exponential
minus one. Okay. So it basically is same
as exponential minus one.
So you wonder why do you you know why do
you have like a function that just do
that minus one you why can't you know
people can just use that minus one if
they want to. So the the reason is
computing in a way that is accurate even
uh when the value of x is close to zero.
So the reason is
when when you do exponential
it um
you know because of the like the
floating point they they they become
inaccurate. Okay.
So you see so these two results are very
close but not the same.
So, but what is the reason I've Oh, God,
I need to think
So when when this value is
when this value is when the input the
argument is close to zero
Then supposedly
the exponential when the value is close
to zero it will give you
like less accurate result.
But why is that? Because when
wait I don't understand.
when exponential zero the result is just
uh one isn't it
what I don't I don't understand
can anyone explain you guys here can you
guys explain
oh god this is confusing
So when you do exponential
when the input is zero
the result is just one. Okay.
Okay. When the when the input is zero,
the result should be just one because
that means e raised to zero. anything
raised to zero result is one.
Okay. So it's you know
okay obviously but um so let's see if w
language will reduce the value there it
is anything any number raised to zero
power zero is one
uh so
So what so why is it you know there's no
nothing abnormal here. So why is it when
the value is near zero it
you know like you know for this
exponential function any value between
you know -2 or two there's no
abnormalities.
So why do you um have this I don't
understand. Okay, let's ask AI. But but
meanwhile, let's also look at the
Mozilla documentation because they will
explain it.
You see, E raised to the power of a
number subtracted by one. Like what?
What the [ __ ]
[laughter]
I don't know. Like what?
This is You see this? This is kind of
the [ __ ] up in programming languages.
You see why is this necessary? Like like
for example if you have you know you
have a function plus right you can add
any number 1 + 1 1 + 2 you can add any
number of numbers
but then as a language designer you say
oh let's add another function plus one
like the C++ [ __ ]
you know well it does the same thing
like C++ you know like plus you know x=
to x + one however uh you know you have
shorter syntax++
and in fact the CPU did we have like
increment we call the register you know
increment um instruction [ __ ] [ __ ] the
CNCP people you see these people so so
it ts the programming language you see
as a programming as a programmer you
don't care what the [ __ ] about the CPU
you care about mathematics that's what
you're
But then then the programming language
for some reason they added this thing
just to as a workar around so because
they can't get it right. So you got this
expM. Okay. Now let let's let's see what
what what exactly is going on. Okay.
Uh
okay. So let's enlarge my font here so
I'm digressing all over. Are you guys
with me? Nobody's commenting.
Uh, customize fonts. Let's see. 26. You
did.
They ignored. Did they ignore my
setting?
Okay, let's say 16. Advanced settings.
Minimum font size.
24.
Okay. Now,
okay. Now, it's you need to minimate
font size. Okay. So, anyway, so let's go
to Mozilla. So, let's see. Mozilla. Go
to it.
Static method returns e raised to the
power of a number subtracted by one.
That is okay. Try it. No, we're going to
not try the [ __ ] after the number return
value number a number representing e to
the x minus one. Where is the base of
the natural logarithm? Description for a
very small value of x. Adding one can
reduce or eliminate precision.
>> [sighs]
>> The double floats used in JavaScript
give you about 15 digits of precision.
Okay.
Adding one for a very small value of x.
Okay. Are you guys like seeing what I'm
saying? Am I still going? Check.
Concurrent view was six. Okay, I'm still
going. Right, guys? Say something.
[gasps] Uh, [sighs]
average view duration 7 minutes.
Okay. So,
okay. So, we going to So, we uh we're
going to figure this out
for for very small value of x.
Okay. So, adding one can reduce or
eliminate precision.
What? What? What what is it talking
about? This is not clear explanation.
The double floats used in JavaScript
gives you about 15 digits of precision.
1 + i minus 15 but I - 16 and therefore
exactly 1.1 in that arithmetic because
digit past 15 are rounded off.
When you calculate e to the x where x is
a number very close to zero,
oh you should get the answer very close
to 1 + uh
yeah
right very close to one
you should get answer very close to that
instead due to the highest significant
figure in the result of math exponential
being the unit digit one.
The final value ends up being that with
only three correct digits. If you
calculate that that that that that that
[ __ ]
the bit diddling [ __ ]
You see this this is a issue
that arose from the C and C++ fuckets.
They went all over. Okay?
You know, they never should be like
that. Okay? Like like what the bit did
[ __ ] That's your problem. You know, you
can't compute. That's your problem.
Bits. We can't do it this way.
Therefore, we need a new function that
do that does the same thing but minus
one. [laughter]
And as a mathematician, you can't even
figure out. It's just like this
shouldn't be anything abnormal. This is
not a abnormal function.
Yeah, but the bit that's a situation.
Okay, that's why I truly despise the
C++. Now, so this interesting question
does this happen in all other languages?
I don't think so. So, this is not a
general case of you know uh of uh
numerical analysis issue.
It's just like particular to JavaScript
because JavaScript
numbers are got problems. Okay. But
wait, what? I don't I still don't
understand. So like so
even from bits point of view, why why
can't you have this um
Hello Kasa. Hello.
Um, okay. So, I I still don't get it.
Okay. There there's some explanation
about the bits, but um
Okay. So, I don't quite understand.
That's one thing. The other thing is
does this happen in Python? That my
question. Okay. Does this happen in
Python? Does it happen in Goland or is
it just just JavaScript? Because as far
as I know JavaScript, you know, we are
talking about floating points here, not
integers.
If you are talking about integers then I
know JavaScript got a problem with
integers because they
you know there's no true integers in
JavaScript but we are talking about
floating point.
So if JavaScript has this problem why
does the same problem occur in Python in
Goland for example? That's a good
question. Let's let's ask AI. Okay.
Okay. We are digressing all over. I'm
not doing what I wanted to do. But um
so let's ask
in JavaScript you have
does this happen in Python or Goland or
F.
So let's magnify the font so you can
see.
Yes, all three languages have an
equivalent to JavaScript's math
exponential m1 which computes e to the x
minus one accurately especially for
small x. So Python
So Python got the same problem. Oh
Jesus. So, Goland Goland's got the same
problem. Oh, okay. So, this is actually
a universal problem.
Uh, okay. So, I'm mistaken. So, this is
this is
kind of due to my ignorance of the bits.
So, in F you also got the problem. So,
you got So, you got that. So, it's
available in modern.net net versions and
provides the same high accuracy
computation. All of them are designed
for numerical stability when x is close
to zero
where plain exponential minus one
loses precision due to float floating
point cancellations. Okay. Uh
okay. I don't quite understand but in
wuam language you don't have this
problem okay that I know for sure
does this problem occur in wra language
the answer is no
what wait yes the same precision loss
problem with exponential minus one for
very small x can occur in wufam language
but wufam handles it better than most
languages thanks to its arbitrary
precision numeric numeric language
provides an internal function for it. Oh
okay. Yeah. So,
so in other words, this problem does not
occur in Wufam language. Okay. Because
they handled it internally because it's
not the programmer's problem. It's the
implement
implementation the implementator's
problem. Okay? You don't bring your
problem to other people. Like if my job
is, you know, to write a compiler, I
don't, oh, I can't do this. Let let the
programmer worry about that's a C C++
[ __ ] Okay.
So better ways in woofer language
because of its powerful arbitrary
precision system you often don't even
need. Yeah of course. Yes. So now the so
the other question does this uh occur in
scheme because as far as I know scheme
usually deal with these kind of issues
too.
Does it occur in scheme disparal
numbers? Okay. I think this is an issue
with floating point math. Decimal
numbers don't have this issue. Yes.
Okay. Does it occur in scheme list? Yes.
the same precision loss problem
exponential minus one for very small x
does occur
in scheme and most okay
so you can see in scheme there's no exp1
function okay so the but the problem
exists with plain exponential x common
list no standard okay problem exist
bracket yes has it building okay So
okay so racket provides this extra
function. Okay.
Okay. Very interesting. Uh use use a
library or implement a simple version
for small x. God this is annoying.
Okay. So this this issue is significant.
Okay. Uh it's rather my ignorance. This
this issue is significant. So I really I
need to understand
why does this occur exactly? Read this
in detail. Okay. I think I'm going to do
it offline.
But wait, but but I I just don't believe
it. Okay. Does it occur in Julia?
The programming language Julia because
that is designed for scientific
programming.
Okay, they all have this exp1.
Uh
very annoying.
You see, so only woo fam language handle
it in a perfect way. But all the others
they kind of like require. Oh, by the
way, if you know if you are computing
near zero, you need to call the other
function.
Is that the case? you know so we can
actually needs to uh
this issue I need to look at deeper
because um you know if I have time
because you know to actually try
different languages
let's let's see so it says Python
let's look at the Python documentation
Open Python documentation local
documentation and let's search for
expm1.
There it is.
Okay. So in math
god very annoying.
Okay.
Let's get back to the here. And uh for
this, let's just uh
Oh god, this is extremely ugly. Okay,
let's plot log. Okay, so now let's just
plot log.
So log so in wam language log is natural
log. So but what do you want? Just log.
Okay. So log x. Uh so let's do that.
Okay. So log is uh yeah zero.
Okay. So you can kind of say six. Go to
six.
Uh
okay. So
Okay. So, that's that.
Let's copy the other one.
go to the JavaScript page and uh let's
go to the log.
This is exponential log. So,
okay,
let's update the date.
Okay, go down.
Go down. Natural log. So, you got that
natural log. And what is this is log
based on 10 power of 10. Okay. So you
need a log based on power of 10. And I
believe that's a second argument that
the ba base.
Yeah.
So
not that.
Uh,
what?
What?
[sighs]
Oh, yeah. This is completely wrong. This
uh
base is the first argument.
Okay. So 10.
Yeah, that's right. So,
but how did we why do we get this funky
thing?
when base is negative. That's right. You
you went to the negative base.
That's why you get this funky part.
Okay. Anyway, so yeah. So um
okay let's say
log 10 base
is ne never uh negative. Okay so let's
do that and let's just do four. Okay,
it's better.
Copy it.
Okay, we got the picture there. And then
you got the log natural log of x + one.
That's another
uh numerical analysis issue.
Oh, wait.
Yeah. Okay. Then you got the log log
two.
So base two logarithm.
Okay. So you got like that through
through the
two to the second power is four.
That's right. So you could have 16.
Mhm.
So let's grit
grid lines.
Uh 16
Because when it's 16, the value is four.
Four times two
is 16. That's base two. So we want grid
lines. Um,
let's make the grid lines.
[sighs]
What's value? So,
That's a list of numbers. No, we don't
want that.
Okay. So for the y is uh let's do
okay that.
So
four and uh
two is four.
8 is
8 is three. That's right.
Okay. that.
Okay, we got one picture, two picture,
third picture, base 10 of log x and
base two of log x.
Okay, finished one thing, one of the
things I want to do today. Okay, close
that uh show in browser. Okay, close
that. Show uh showing browser today's
talk show.
So floating point math arbitrary
precision ara decimal numbers. Yes,
[snorts]
that is the topic of numerical analysis.
Okay,
because in actually I learned this I
learned some of the detail about this
only recently.
Basically the issue the the issue is
part of numerical analysis. The issue is
when you have decimal numbers like the
way we write a number like 3.123
something.
Uh but in computers you have to
represent them as binary numbers. you
know one zero is one zero and um so but
binary numbers cannot represent floating
numbers
precisely without infinite repetition.
So in a similar situation you can see
for example 1 over three 1 over three
1/3 of a pi let's say you have a pizza
you could three people sharing a pizza
so each person gets one/3 one over three
but in decimal numbers you cannot
represent that number you see what you
know what you get is 0.3333
repeats for forever okay [snorts] now in
binary numbers can Do you represent one
over three? Um
I believe not. Okay. Uh
I mean basically similar situation
happens. Let's ask guac
in binary B I N A R Y can you
how to
represent 1 over3 ask
actually I should talk to uh AI because
that's fun one over three in binary is
the repeating fraction 0.01
0101.
Okay, [laughter]
that's interesting. 0.001
repeats forever. So the bottom line the
bottom line is that given a number a
rational number like like a fraction
depending on the number base you know
for some number base you know you you're
going to have the repeating forever
issue. Okay. So but when we write a
decimal like like for example um
uh when we write the decimal number uh
let's say
0.5
what was it 0.9 I mean anyway decimal
number okay 0.5 now but in binary it may
repeat forever so you cannot represent
accurately
Um
so anyway so it's going to go into math.
So this is a math field called numerical
analysis. Okay. And uh
let's talk to Guac.
It's taking forever. Grog is having a
problem.
Hi, Grog. Can you talk?
How do you represent 0.5 in binary?
Now it's exactly 0.1 in binary. What are
some decimal numbers that cannot be
represented exactly in finite number of
binary digits?
Stop.
Try again.
God.
Okay.
Now, let's refresh.
Show me some examples of decimal numbers
that cannot be represented in binary as
finite number of digits.
Here
are some common ones. 1/3 0.0101
plus missed open end some error sofa and
end quick repeating forever. 1/5 011
011 repeating negative 1 washi pot
0.00110011
of room has viscame away fits. These are
like how 1/3 is 0.333 originally in
decimal. They never end in binary.
Show the corresponding decimal number
>> 1/3 is 0.333
across the enhance allotted new
well 011
01 yield scenery you'd bring it for a
long part but in binary it's 0101
repeating forever 1/5 is 0.2 2 in
decimal, but in binary it's 0.001
1 0 011 repeating. 1/10th is 0.1 in
decimal, but in binary it's 0.00001
1 0 0 1 0 1 0 capital 1 1 repeating.
Okay, so that's some example. So uh so
let's go back here
and see
add plot to that we did. Uh what's the
next thing to do? Uh redo the image in
wam language. Okay. So I have this page.
I want to redo that image.
Uh that image is done in uh graphing
calculator like 20 years ago. Okay. So
let's redo it. Okay. So
Okay.
Pre
uh what? There's no pre. Okay. So code
what are we doing here? Okay.
Okay. Let's do
Okay.
Okay. So actually
so what I want to show here is this
value is equals to E. So e the capital E
in woofer language is how you represent
the exponential number.
Okay. Now you evaluate it will return
true. Okay. There was a matched bracket.
Okay. What?
No there is true. So why a match bracket
warning Emac. Okay issue.
Paste it. shift enter. So you can see
return true control shift N to make it
um
type set. So you can see so okay so
that's true. So that's the definition of
the E and but however what I want to do
here is to plot it. So uh plot
so you want to plot e raised to the
exponential um now is there a
exponential function I mean instead of
just e to the power. So
okay so there is easy gives the
exponential
of Z.
Let's see
exponential automatically evaluate to
exact value math function suitable for
both symbolic and numerical computation.
Okay. EZ is converted to E raised to E.
Yeah. So they are identical in wuam
language.
I mean the syntax. Okay.
So you can just say
you know here you just say e ra to
raised to uh x. Okay. And let's delete
that. And x uh from let's say -2 to two.
Okay. and let's say auto uh
aspect ratio
automatic. Okay, go back to wam
language. Paste it. Run it. Uh plot
points. You got a problem.
Uh plot end points for X
must have distinct machine precision.
What?
Oh, negative. Yeah, obviously not -22.
I mean -22. Not -2 to -2. So there it
is. So you this is huge.
Shrink it.
Okay. So then you add grid again. Oh
god.
Okay. So, let's try it. Create lines
automatic. Let's see how it does.
Okay.
Yeah, let's let's let that be that.
Okay. So here is two this. So
exponential function.
Okay. And let's copy the formula the
full formula here. Copy.
So that
there that's the one we used. Move it
down.
Syntax collect showing browser. So there
we have a new uh plot.
The old one actually looks better.
Funny.
Uh yeah,
you see. So yeah, the old one actually
looks better, but um
so what are the range? So okay, so this
one goes from -2 -4 to there's a lot of
tension went into -4 to three.
So if you go from -4 to
three.
Yeah, now it looks slightly better.
Okay.
So, and uh then you want to go then you
if you want to really purify you have to
do plot range
plot range. Um
so you know like how much you include in
the plot. So -4 2
uh -4 23 and the vertical axis would be
-1 to uh -1 to
let's say 13. Okay.
But but now you increase this.
Let's say five.
Uh, wait.
Four. Shift. Enter.
No. Fantastic. Now that's beautiful.
Okay, that is what we want. Okay, copy
that.
Copy that.
Showing browser. Okay, we did that. and
uh
that we can uh
oh god this is ugly what we doing so we
are doing exponential curve
okay so this one
uh this one oh yeah so this one xxp P.
Okay, we got three plots. The third one
looks better.
Okay, so let's remove this one.
Delete. And this one,
and delete it.
Okay. But you also have
Let's leave it. Okay. So there.
Okay. We did that.
Okay. So, what are we doing
next?
Okay, we did that.
I'm not really happy with the images
because they look
they don't look good.
Yeah, let's leave it. Okay. So, anyway,
so that we did close that. And then
what's the next thing I want to do?
The next thing I want to do is we want
plain curves add a new page and on hyp
hyperbolic functions cinch co
etc. Link for my JavaScript math
hyperbolic function page. Okay.
uh new page.
Okay. So you're talking about plan
curves project. So that would be here.
So in this page you need to add more
new.
Okay. So
okay.
So you got this page. You need to add a
new page.
Hyperbolic sign hyperbolic trick
functions.
So the problem is
uh my my curve page there is no page of
hyperbolic trick functions
which is a huge um
missing page. Well, the reason I don't
have that is because back then 30 years
ago,
I did not want to add information that
is common
uh common in textbooks.
So, for example,
uh well, it's kind of hard to explain.
Well, not that exactly hard to explain.
You see, you want to
stand out. So anyway, so I didn't
include, you know, basic information
kind of like that.
So I have the sign curve even the trig
functions much of these uh you know this
very interesting uh sign there's a lot
rich formulas and ident identities but
even these basic ones back then I did
not include much of it
uh but only more like more interesting
ones
uh for example there's no trick
identities on this page
But um
anyway, so what what am I saying? So so
what uh what do I want to do? So yeah,
so I'm missing a hyperbolic function
page.
Um
I mean hyperbolic functions. Yes. And I
want to add it.
Oh god.
So every time
It's easier said than than done because
every time I was planning this, you
know, I was just saying, "Oh, yeah, I
need this page. Let's add it."
But then in in actual live stream,
you know, to add that page will
[ __ ] I'm out of drink.
Involve
a lot work actually not you know
actually I can just start it
uh but
because then I have this page
uh this page is JavaScript.
So one of the thing I need to do is to
actually add So I need to add the images
for each one of these and add a sample
code like how do you actually call okay
let's add a sample code here
okay so here is the image uh and you
need actual sample code okay JavaScript
and uh that will be math Path sync
completion. There it is. And what value
should we try? Let's say one. Okay. One.
And you need console log to print it
because it's JavaScript. Now predefine
the code.
Run it. There is a value. Okay. Now put
it back. Synax color it show in browser.
So now we have a example of how do you
you know just to show just to show how
um
you know like have an actual code
example.
But now we need to have all of these um
or should I just have one? Let's just
have one for now.
Uh but then you want you want the graph.
Okay. So should I I can add a graph one
for each one of them here or
like I was planning to or go here create
a new uh page and create hyperbolic.
Yeah, you need to do it. Okay, because
Okay, let's do it.
Okay, let's go to the directory. So, you
want uh
so what do you want to do? So, new
directory.
Uh let's uh call it cinch.
Okay.
Oh, where? Wait, there is already a
cinch. What?
Okay. So I already So actually I did
this. This is must be
longer than 15 years ago. So I already
have a page.
So I want to update it. Now this is done
by the graphing calculator. So I need to
update the image. And uh okay let's plot
the image. Okay let's yeah copy it.
Close
it. Hyperbolic trig functions. Okay. So
that is the graph. Close. Close. Close.
Close.
Exponential curve. Close. Paste that
here. Okay. Go to it and uh let's do a
woofam language. That's right. So let's
do wam language. Okay. Then you just you
want to plot like before.
Uh you want now this time you want to
plot several functions. Let's see. Are
you going to plot all of them together?
Yes. Why not? Okay. So you can actually
copy them.
Okay. Uh hyperbolic trick functions.
That's what they are. And let's uh
let's delete uh let's delete the delete
that that that okay let's just say x so
each one of them needs this x
you are plotting six curves okay and
then uh then uh so what is the range
-5 to five that's a size range. Okay. -5
to
five. Okay. And uh you want automatic of
course aspect ratio.
Okay. And you want uh
leave it then what you want? Um
we can actually just try this. Okay.
It's going to plot uh six
curves in one image
in one shot.
Okay, it looks like that. Not bad. Now
the
Now let's do plot range. It's limit what
uh
plot range x and y goes from
uh 0 five to five. Is that right?
And the yaxis goes from what what is the
value? Let's say four to four. Let's say
5 to 52.
Okay. Copy. Copy that
and uh do it. Okay, now it's much
better. Now you want to plot legends.
Okay, this is Yeah. So, how do you do
labels? Legend labels. I don't know.
Uh
so they use the word label. Okay. So
let's look up
uh you need an example. Okay. So let's
let's let's just
look up examples. There's a lot examples
plot very basic function. Okay. Move
from language.
And
so there's plot legends and plot labels.
Overall label for the plot label to use
for curves. Okay. a legend for curves.
So there's got labels.
Okay. So one way to do it is like that.
Okay. So let's see that's one way or
alternatively
like that.
Copy.
Go back here.
Shift enter. Okay. You got some option
problem. You missing a comma there.
Shift enter.
Okay. So now it's better. That's
but it's not
using a plot range value.
Why not? I don't know.
and uh co-angent seeant tangent.
Okay, that's too many. Okay, so let's
try six
to six.
Okay, maybe maybe there's too many
things going on. So, let's try to reduce
it.
Uh
maybe that'll be more
manageable.
Yes, you see.
So, this above. So, let's see.
Now there's some issue about
how do you want to arrange the labels.
Okay. So you can do it above or plot
labels automatic. Okay. So let's not use
placed
plot labels just automatic.
Oh god, it's got this funky thing. I
don't like it.
Easy.
Now, how do you how do you make it like
with color?
So, plug labels is one way. What's the
other way?
So
plot label
and if you say below So,
what would that do?
Better.
No,
because the co there,
let's say left.
Now it's perfect.
Now this is perfect. You see? So you got
cinch. Okay. So you need to This is
perfect.
Now let's add grids.
Great lines automatic.
Fantastic. I like this. Okay. So now
let's copy that.
that. Okay.
So now
now you can plot seeant coseant
cotangent
hyper hyperbolic
co. Wait, what?
Oh, so you got wow you got seeant. Wow,
those are you know so many
you know these are hyperbolic version of
trig functions. So
then you have the inverse functions for
each. So they are like 12 of them.
Uh
but for now let's say that and uh let's
do that
and syntax collect show in browser.
Fantastic. Okay.
So let's see you know let's compare them
side by side so that
yeah so kosh Oh [ __ ]
Now that's good. Okay. Delete that.
Yeah. So that's good. That's This is
more
like you can actually understand what's
going on. S
c
tangent.
That's right.
tangent is define tangent hyperbolic
tangent is defined by hyperbolic sign
over hyperbolic cosine.
So hyperbolic sign. So they are close to
one. When the value be is greater than
one they are
close to one ratio of one. But when they
are below one then kosh is larger. So
they get you know smaller
becomes zero. Then when it's negative
the cinch
hyperbolic sign
is negative and uh so you have the same
situation except the sign is negative.
So you got this green line. Fantastic.
Okay. Understand? So this now this looks
pretty but it's uh deleted. Okay.
hyperbolic trick functions. Delete it.
Okay. Then uh delete that.
Show in browser. Okay. Just that. Okay.
That's the how you plot it.
Uh hyperbolic trick. Okay. So,
so actually
let's say
let's name the graph. Okay. So, let's
name it just um
so
rename the plot and uh remove the year.
Uh do I should I have the date there?
Usually no.
I mean the date for usually I keep the
date because then you kind of know when
did you generate this image so that
let's say 10 years after 20 years after
when people look at this page you know
kind of what year it is generated like
today if you look at the old
documentation you have no idea is is
like 1990s or is it from 1960s
but if you have a year then you
C. Oh, so this is you know gives you an
idea what year it is created. So you you
you get information like of that era it
you know the software or whatever looks
like that.
So anyway so so we did this. So this is
what I wanted to do. Okay. So that's
kind of that's done. Then there is some
mathematical information today. Okay,
you just go to Wikipedia, you have a lot
more rich information. Okay, so here I'm
trying to talk about the definition
you know to write things like that it
takes tremendous time. It takes more
than a week to for example create this
page explaining just the basics of
hyperbolic functions.
But anyway, yeah, so it takes tremendous
time to actually write it.
But Wikipedia you know you have
thousands of thousand people doing it
together. So
um mostly students you know and uh they
done that in the past
25 years.
So if you don't know
you know just search for Wikipedia
because I I have done so. So um
search you'll see Wikipedia hyperbolic
functions and today with uh AI they are
hyperbolic functions. So you you have a
plot very well done explanation
definitions and all kind of details.
It's actually fantastic
hyperbolic trig functions.
Uh
yeah. So anyway, so that's my page.
So close that. Now let's see what else I
want to do. I think I'm done for today.
We did at least some of it. Okay, some
like some of the things I want to do. Uh
we do the image. We did that in wam
language. So let's summarize what we
did. Okay. So first of all we looked
into this book JavaScript in depth
actual book
by James Snail. Okay. And we I talked
about my work JavaScript in depth.
Okay. Then his book this guy you can
trust him. I I think so. And then there
is the oh someone is creating a emac
you know a new emac. So I have some
stories to tell you got to be careful.
Okay. Then uh then common list V emac
schemax. Then uh we did
we did plot the logarithmic functions
and exponential functions. And we spend
some 20 minutes to look into
numerical analysis issues about
and programming language design issues
about
the
binary digits. you know when when you
cannot have when you have errors when
you deal with
uh decimal notation in binary digit then
you got issues like very complicated
numerical analysis issues. So
uh
okay so we plotted the graphs we talked
we looked into some of the issues that
apparently occur in all programming
languages in Python in Goland in because
they all have this exponential minus one
thing. So we ask AI for it. Where is our
AI here? So here is our AI question. So
I'm going to save it. Okay. And put on
my page.
So let's write it down. So we discussed.
So we discussed Yeah. So what?
Okay. So what?
So let's go there. Exp.
Yeah. So
discuss why we need
ask AI
occur
in Python colisp
common disp and racket disp
uh it so happen.
So we discussed that
and uh then we um
then we created a page. We we plotted
this uh
well we didn't plot but we did we
created the
we plotted that
and in fact I can add that image to this
JavaScript page. So it that would be
good and actually I need to do the
inverse. So you got the yeah so you see
co tangent of sign uh then you got the
inverse version that you should plot
okay we haven't done but um so you need
to plot the inverse of each of these
function
which is not difficult. Okay. So this is
actually so this is not difficult. So we
can let's let's try it.
Um
yeah, you kind of need So you see you
got all these um
let's leave it. Okay, I'm going to do it
offline. So,
so then
then we did uh add code example, okay,
for one of them. Okay, I think that's it
for today. Thank you guys for watching
whatever you guys are doing.
Um,
yeah, I think we did that for today.
Bye, guys.
>> [snorts]
>> So on this page you need that graph.
Okay. So on this page you need
uh you need
you kind of need that page. So go back
here. So go back here. Uh go back here.
Showing browser.
Okay. So you can
you can link here.
Uh wait, what?
Uh did you just um
copy close?
Go here.
Paste link file. Okay, there is a link
and here is a graph.
And uh then
you don't need this.
Do I need it? No.
Uh
okay. Anyway, that's it. Bye, guys.
>> [snorts]